<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Alter Britanniæ heros: or The life of the most honourable knight, Sir Henry Gage, late Governour of Oxford, epitomiz'd.</title>
            <author>Walsingham, Edward, d. 1663.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97082</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W648</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E303_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200291</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861097</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861097</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113225</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97082)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113225)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 50:E303[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Alter Britanniæ heros: or The life of the most honourable knight, Sir Henry Gage, late Governour of Oxford, epitomiz'd.</title>
                  <author>Walsingham, Edward, d. 1663.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Leonard Lichfield, printer to the Vniversitie.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Edward Walsingham, whose name appears on page 24, appended to an elegy.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept: 25th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gage, Henry, --  Sir, ca. 1597-1645 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649. --  Biography --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113225:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Alter Britanniae Heros:</hi> OR THE LIFE OF THE MOST HONOVRABLE KNIGHT, Sir <hi>HENRY GAGE,</hi> Late Governour of OXFORD, Epitomiz'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by LEONARD LICHFIELD, <hi>Printer to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie.</hi> 1645.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb facs="tcp:113225:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113225:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Alter Britanniae Heros:</hi> OR, THE LIFE AND DEATH OF The moſt Honourable Noble Knight, Sir HENRY GAGE, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>ILL I began ſeriouſly to conſider the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of man in ſuch excellent Perſons as are men indeed, I took that ſaying of the great <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> to taſt more of Paſſion, then Divinity; Wherein he averrs, That were not thoſe well inſtructed by Faith, who duly weigh man, what gifts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces God hath endow'd him withall, what Wonders he hath done to make him great and happy, what Beauties he hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill'd both into Soule and Body, and what ſupereminent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light he takes to be doing good to this Noble Creature; They would conclude, <hi>That Man were the God of God himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now though Faith be to me a precious allay to that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame Concluſion, yet I confeſſe the ſentence to be a certain truth. This I was compell'd to acknowledge, when I did ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey exactly the Excellencies of a <hi>Smith,</hi> or <hi>Gage,</hi> to recount examples to my ſelfe familiar, and ſuch as I may ſpeak of ſafely under the Character of a gratefull vertue; Cenſure her ſelfe granting it a Soleciſme to flatter the dead.</p>
            <p>Pardon my generous ambition of two ſuch Noble Mottoes as <hi>Fidelity</hi> and <hi>Gratitude</hi> afford: whereto that I want not ſome pretence, I call you to witneſſe, O great and happy <hi>Geniees</hi> of the two forementioned <hi>Heroes.</hi> To peerleſſe <hi>Smith,</hi> I have
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113225:3"/> already for both thoſe Titles done that homage, which now I am about to pay unto admired <hi>Gage.</hi> Wherein may affection ſupply what the want of leaſure, inſtructions, and the times abridge.</p>
            <p>This gallant Gentleman was borne at <hi>London,</hi> about the yeare 1597. of worthy and exemplar Parents, both of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and noble Families, his Father being a principall Branch of the <hi>Gages</hi> of <hi>Suſſex:</hi> a houſe for Antiquity and merit, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe then obſcure; They were both intent to breed him, with the reſt of their Children, as Gentilely and Civilly, as the Exigence of their Eſtate, Conſumed, and Exhauſted, by the ſeverity of that difficult time would permit.</p>
            <p>And to this end at ten yeares old, ſent him with his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into <hi>Flanders,</hi> to receive Education, where M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Henry Gage,</hi> with ſingular ſatisfaction, paſt through the ſeverall Schooles of <hi>Humanity.</hi> Which accompliſht, he was ſent by his Father through <hi>France</hi> into <hi>Italy,</hi> where under that famous Scholar <hi>Picolhomini,</hi> Vncle to this great Generall, the <hi>Duke of Amalfi,</hi> he heard his <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> and with great applauſe did publiquely defend it. Thus having laid ſtately Ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workes for ſuch Magnificent Structures, as after he raiſed upon them, and being ready to write <hi>Man,</hi> he begins to conſider in what Channell of the Ocean of this World he had beſt ſteer his Courſe towards the Land of Promiſe. At length the divine directions work upon thoſe Noble faculties of his Soule; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Fortitude, and deſire of Honour: inſomuch that between them a firme reſolution is begotten to Sayle towards Heaven over the moſt turbulent part of the <hi>Sea,</hi> in a Man of Warre. He deſignes himſelfe for a Souldier; and conſidering that Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile did much conduce to that end; To <hi>Flanders, France,</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> which he had already view'd, he adde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Germany,</hi> and returnes that way to the <hi>Netherlands.</hi> But leaſt you may judge that of his Travayles he made onely a preſent delight, and fed his Curioſity, I muſt aſſure you his obſervation was ſo ſtrong, and punctuall, that all men did admire the exact account he was able to render of all things deſerving ſerious memory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mars</hi> had now read many bloudy Lectures to the <hi>Belgians,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:113225:3"/> and that Country of all others in <hi>Europe,</hi> was held his proper <hi>Academy.</hi> Where immediately upon his arrivall at 22 yeares of Age; The <hi>Gages glory,</hi> enters himſelfe a Souldier in <hi>Ant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werp Caſtle;</hi> There for a Twelve-months ſpace he trayl'd a Pike, where his Noble, diſcreet, and gallant Carriage, brought him ſuch endearments with the Governour and Garriſon, as was very ſingular, and ſeldome gain'd by ſtrangers in ſo high a manner from the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Nation.</p>
            <p>Here his reputation ſhines with ſuch a ſplendor, that the <hi>Earle of Argyle</hi> being about to raiſe a Regiment, ſeeks to win him to him: and offers him a Company. His <hi>Governour</hi> to Congratulate his advancement, Feaſts him in a Princely man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and well preſaging what he would arrive to; publiquely glories to have been Tutor to ſo brave a Souldier.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bergen ap Some,</hi> is the firſt place where he enters into Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, at which Siege being divers times Commanded to aſſault the Enemies Trenches, he gallantly performed it, till at length he was by one of their Mines blowne up towards thoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall Regions whither his Noble Soule aſpired. But it pleaſed God ſtrangely to preſerve him, ſo that his hurt was not ſo dangerous, but that admitted of a ſhort recovery. The next yeare, the Famous <hi>Marqueſſe Spinola</hi> laies ſiege to <hi>Breda<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> in all which long and tedious action, our youthfull <hi>Captain</hi> comports himſelfe, with ſo much Valour, and ſuch Reſolution, that he merited ſpeciall notice from that Renowned Generall. This Siege compleated, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Regiments were both refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, ſo that for two or three yeares he remained without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Charge, and betook himſelfe, if it were poſſible, to a more excellent imployment, The <hi>Theory</hi> of Warre; for his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment told him, practice without Contemplation, was an acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent without a ſubſtance. Sometimes for recreation he caſt an eye upon <hi>Heraldry,</hi> and ſoon therein became a great Profici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. Sometimes he beſtow'd himſelfe in tranſlating Bookes, which he exceeding well perform'd, witneſſe the <hi>Siege of Breda,</hi> written by the elegant <hi>Hermannus Hugo;</hi> and <hi>Vincents Heraldry,</hi> the firſt whereof he tranſlated out of <hi>Latine</hi> into <hi>Engliſh.</hi> The latter out of <hi>Engliſh</hi> into <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:113225:4"/>
            <p>In this Vacation he began to caſt about to find a Conſort, on whom to place his nobleſt affections, and at length he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers one Miſtris <hi>Mary Daniell,</hi> a Gentlewoman, whoſe worth and beauty made her a deſerved object for the Love of ſo excellent a Perſon. It ſeemes nature had long before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd her for him, as we may almoſt conclude, by a memorable accident happening, when with her Mother ſhee long before came over to ſee <hi>London,</hi> the Epitome of this Kingdome. Amongſt other places in the City, which their Curioſity ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veid was S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Jameſe's,</hi> where in a Gallery adorn'd with divers Pictures, they ſaw one of Sir <hi>John Gage's</hi> Knight of the <hi>Garter,</hi> and great Grandfather to the Gentleman that now I write of; who in <hi>Queene Maries</hi> dayes had been Lord <hi>Chamberlaine</hi> of the Houſhold. Of this Picture, the young Gentlewoman took ſpeciall notice, as that which onely pleaſed her, and ſeverall times reviewed it; preſaging as it were that from that ſtrange ſympathy and liking would come ſome ſtrange reſult, as after proov'd by her Match with one deſcended of his Loynes. However then it made ſo firme an Impreſſe on her tender fancy, being then ſcarce twelve yeares old, that after being married, and her Noble Husband paſſionately complaining, that he could not after curious ſearch and labour, find the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of this Sir <hi>John Gage,</hi> which he had ſought for with great deſire: ſhee preſently repeats the former Story, and ſo directs him thither, where ſince he did procure it.</p>
            <p>By this Gentlewoman he had a gallant Fortune, and was bleſt in the proceſſe of thoſe nineteene yeares they liv'd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a dozen Children, whereof ſixe are ſtill living, two Sonnes and foure Daughters. The firmneſſe of their love, and happineſſe was ſuch, that thoſe who liv'd for moſt part with them, and exactly noted what paſt between them, never could obſerve from either the leaſt glance of anger ordiſtaſt: but ſtill diſcover their endleſſe affection in the higheſt <hi>Meridian.</hi> As he was a moſt tender Husband, ſo there never was a more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent Father, which Indulgence he mannag'd with ſuch an high diſcretion, that he preſerv'd in them ſo great a reverence, that a beck or caſt of his eye, was a ſufficient command or check
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113225:4"/> unto them. But he taught them this filiall piety, not onely by precept, but example alſo, as appeares by a memorable act of his about this time, for his Father through his great misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, was brought unto the hard condition of Confiſcation of his whole Eſtate, and long impriſonment, having onely his life left him, and that onely upon curteſie, by the Kings reprieve after Condemnation. In this caſe he had not onely outliv'd his owne remainder of ſubſiſtance; but alſo the ſeverall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuities his Noble Allies and Kindred had beſtowed upon him, ſome for 20, ſome for 30 yeares, in pure Compaſſion to ſee his endleſſe Sufferings.</p>
            <p>But his Durance hath ſurvived all, and no reliefe is left him, but the generous piety of his Worthieſt Sonne, who to relieve his Fathers Exigence, voluntarily demiſes the reverſion of a faire Eſtate at <hi>Croyden,</hi> called <hi>Haling-houſe,</hi> waving all reſpect of wrong to himſelfe, or prejudice to his Wife and Children: ſo farre did the force of his unequall'd piety to his Parents, tranſport his Noble nature.</p>
            <p>Having paſt now two or three yeares<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> without any active or publick imployment, and furniſh't his Contemplation with the beſt Maximes of Warre, he thinkes fit to fall againe to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe thoſe choycer Meditations wherewith he had enricht his mind. In the yeare 1630, Sir <hi>Edward Parham</hi> raiſing a new Regiment of <hi>Engliſh,</hi> makes Sir <hi>William Threſham</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant <hi>Major,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Gage</hi> Captaine <hi>Commendant,</hi> in which condition he remained, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill by <hi>Parham's</hi> death, <hi>Treſham</hi> came to ſucceed as <hi>Colonell,</hi> and <hi>Captaine Gage</hi> as <hi>Sergeant Major,</hi> in which imployment he was, when the <hi>States</hi> beſiedged <hi>Maſtricht;</hi> where the <hi>Marqueſſe de Sanct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cruce</hi> won, with the gallantry, and prudence of the <hi>Commanders,</hi> in theſe deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate times did ſo re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye upon that Regiment, that he gave them the guard of his owne Perſon.</p>
            <p>The next yeare he was in the Field, with the <hi>Marqueſſe de Aitona,</hi> in that which they called the running <hi>Leaguer,</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the <hi>States</hi> and their continuall motion. Where the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned <hi>Marqueſſe,</hi> with the <hi>Duke de L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> took ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ciall notice of him, that they perſwaded him to raiſe a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113225:5"/> of his owne: and to that end gave him a Commiſſion. But by reaſon of ſome difficulties in <hi>England,</hi> it could not be throughly effected, till a little before Sir <hi>William Threſhams</hi> death. When he having raiſed above 900 effective men, the others death intervening, had his Regiment compleated by addition of the old unto it; which his <hi>Highneſſe the Prince Cardinall</hi> beſtowed upon him. But theſe favours and endeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments amongſt Strangers he obtained not by any ſiniſter meanes, but meerly with the eminence of his Vertue, for he could not be won to doe any thing ungratefull to his naturall Soveraigne: or inconſiſtent with the intereſt and honour of his Nation. Witneſſe his fidelity expreſt by his ſpeedy repaire to <hi>England</hi> out of <hi>Flanders,</hi> (where he was in actuall Service by licenſe of his Soveraigne) as ſoon as our King had broken Peace with <hi>Spaine,</hi> and called his Subjects home. This I am confident you may find once or twice atteſted upon record, by ſuch Miniſters of State as then were reſident in <hi>Flanders.</hi> A good teſtimony of his Loyalty and obedience, who upon the firſt Summons of his King did not diſpute the matter, but readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly left his whole Fortunes behind him, yea his Wife and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren as well as his Command there, which was alwayes honourable.</p>
            <p>What I hence inferre, was confirmed by another preſident, which I ſhall wrong his memory to omit. For when the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Regiment in <hi>Flanders,</hi> was Commanded into <hi>Germany;</hi> the prudent and gallant <hi>Colonell</hi> ſenſible of his Countries In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, ſtoutly refuſed that imployment; alledging it to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable for <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects to maintaine a Warre in the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> againſt the Nephewes of their owne Soveraigne. And this aſſeveration he fortified with ſuch evincing reaſons, that he prevailed to have that Command repeal'd: an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that nothing was more deare unto him, then his duty to his Prince and Country.</p>
            <p>Whil'ſt he was <hi>Colonell,</hi> his Regiment was every Summer in the Field, and put upon the moſt important Actions; As for the Siege of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Omers,</hi> his memory in thoſe that make relation of it, muſt needs be very eminent; ſince it is held Confeſt,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113225:5"/> that his Trudence and Valour, did not onely make good the Townes ſo long reſiſtance, but alſo was the load<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſtarre, which guided <hi>Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olhomini</hi> to that proſperous ſucceſſe in their reliefe.</p>
            <p>Three Summers ſucceſſively, was he imployed to ſuccour <hi>Gueldres,</hi> before which the <hi>States</hi> Army lay, whence ſtill he returned with proſperous and deſerved ſucceſſe. After the <hi>Spaniards</hi> had loſt the Bartaile of <hi>Re Croyx,</hi> he was ſent with his Regiment and 1400 other Horſe and Foot to ſecure <hi>Guel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derland,</hi> againſt the <hi>Hollander,</hi> who was thought likely to take the advantage of that defeat, and endeavour to effect ſomething there. But they having notice who was deſigned to attend them, wav'd their deſigne, and returned back with their Army into <hi>Flanders:</hi> which was likewiſe done by this prudent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, who returned with ſuch unexpected celerity, that he came happily to joyne with <hi>Don Franciſco de Melos</hi> Army, before the Enemy was able to effect any thing. Afterwards, <hi>Don Andreas Cantelmo</hi> took him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and two other <hi>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> De Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po,</hi> and marcht out of <hi>Flanders</hi> with them, to the Skirts of <hi>Holland,</hi> where after they had every where given ſtrong A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmes, in their returne home <hi>Cantelmo</hi> ſent him to take in a Caſtle poſſeſſed by the <hi>States.</hi> Which he did, forcing the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants to render upon diſcretion; notwithſtanding which he uſed them with ſo much generoſity, that during their Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, he entertained the Officers every day at his owne Table, and procured moreover for them and the Common Souldiers, who were above 100<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in number a da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly allowance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> from the Country, which noble Curteſie of his, moved the <hi>Prince of Orange,</hi> to uſe divers principall Officers <hi>Spaniards,</hi> tal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> at the latter end of that yeares field, with like Civility.</p>
            <p>Whilſt thus he was growing every day in eſteeme and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, amongſt the moſt judicious and eminent of thoſe that knew him, and being now looked upon by all ſuch as he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſt with as a moſt accompliſht Gentleman, and compleat Souldier. This horrid and unnaturall Rebellion breakes forth at home, which from the beginning he did ſo much reſent, that with all poſſible induſtry he imployed his utmoſt power and abilities in <hi>Flanders,</hi> to further and advance the quarrell of his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113225:6"/> diſtreſſed Soveraigne; and to ſupplant the <hi>Rebells.</hi> As he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc't by his many painfull and coſtly endeavours, which at ſundry times deprived the <hi>Rebells</hi> of neare 30000 Armes, and afforded His Majeſty 8000 of thoſe that were intended to be borne againſt him; nay had been doubtleſſe had not Noble <hi>Colonell Gage</hi> diverted the intention, ſeized them to a better uſe, and made the action an eternall Argument of his Loyalty and Prudence.</p>
            <p>But this was not the onely inſtance he gave of his affection to his King, whoſe ſervice he tendered ſo much, that although his Regiment was then much weakned, and he deprived of hopes to recruit it, never any Souldier of his, who could give him any probable hopes of attaining His Majeſties Army, but he chearfully gave him his paſſe, and encouragement to depart. Whence I dare ſafely affirme, that ſince theſe Ciyill Warres, that Regiment hath afforded His <hi>Majeſty</hi> at leaſt 200 Officers of ſeverall degrees.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding all this, he did not conceive he had done his part as he ought, unleſſe he came in Perſon to ſerve his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne alſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which conſideration he ſo deeply apprehended, that neither his preſent imployment, aſſurance of future pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, a reputation ſo eminent, a revenue ſo ſure and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, nay nor his Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and Children could deta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e him: but he take<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> leave of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> and repaires to <hi>England,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving to contribute all that <hi>Magazine</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> abilities wherewith his breaſt was ſtored to the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oring of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries happineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he comes not emp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y handed, Armes, and divers Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of quality gave ſome addition to the welcome of that moſt worthy and endearing Perſon of his. He was received with joy at the Court, and (every one preſaging he ſhould ſhortly doe his Nation ſome eminent Service) intert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ined here with a welcome <hi>Omen.</hi> Where his prudent, civill, and gallant Converſation, added ſuch a L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tre unto his other Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and ſeated him ſo much above the region of envy, that malice her ſelfe durſt not barefact chooſe but fawne upon him. Soone had he fortified himſelfe in the judgement of the King
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113225:6"/> and the ableſt men about him, as alſo wedded the Peoples opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. And now every ones impatient, till by ſome gallant action; he hath paid tribute for the great eſteem, and reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they had fixt upon him.</p>
            <p>Whil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt every one is caſting about for ſome imployment worthy of him, His Majeſty conſidering the exigence of his owne preſent Condition, and the importance of <hi>Oxford,</hi> his Principall Garriſon, is neceſſitated to engage the Colonell joyntly with the Governour Sir <hi>Arthur Aſhton,</hi> in the defence and preſervation of it. In the Interim of which imployment, what great and memorable things he did, in the ſubſequent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe I will relate. No one is ignorant, that knew any thing, what excellent things he did propoſe for the Fortifying, Clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, Storing, and preſerving the City. How many grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces he publickly remov'd in the Officers, and endeavour'd to reforme: and what worthy endeavours he did uſe to regulate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and moderate the reciprocall abuſes, and exceſſes that were ſo obviouſly committed.</p>
            <p>Whil'ſt we are thus buſied within our walls, the induſtrious Rebells ſeek to environ us on all ſides, and ſo by Famine force us to ſurrender. Wherefore to this end they clap a Garriſon into <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſtall houſe,</hi> within ſixe miles of us on that ſide whence moſt of our Proviſions came. Beſides this, whilſt His Majeſty was abſent in the field, they fortify <hi>Abington,</hi> beſiege <hi>Banbury,</hi> and ſtraiten <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s every way, ſo that we are compell'd for our neceſſary ſubſiſtance to endeavour their repulſe on ſome ſide. After Conſultation, <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſtall</hi> is thought the fitteſt to be attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and <hi>Colonell Gage</hi> muſt be entruſted with the manage of that buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>They allow him a Competence of men, and other neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>June</hi> he ſets forward, where after his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivall with his owne Perſonall Valour, he put ſuch Courage into his Followers; and with his prudent ordering of all things ſo amated the conſcious Enemy: that he ſoone brought them to a Parly. His Carriage in the buſineſſe deſerving a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act relation, I will take leave to diſcend to partioulars. The 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day in the morning, he ſate downe before the Houſe,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113225:7"/> immediatly ſending word to the Lady, that ſhee and others of her Sexe might depart thence with leave and ſafety: promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to ſee her ſafely convoyed to any place ſhee had a mind to. His excelling curteſie was ſuch, that though this Lady did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe then merit ſuch an offer, he could not diſpence with the goodneſſe of his owne nature, to deprive her of this civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. Aſſoone as he had notice that the Ladies were gone, the Houſe was preſently inviron'd by his Command, and the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers fell on with ſuch a well-govern'd fury, that they ſoon poſſeſſed the Church and other out buildings, which the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my endeavoured to defend: but thence repelled, and ſeeing the Houſe attempted with hot aſſault, Conducted by ſo much diſcretion, and exemplary Courage of the Commander; they demand a Parly, and offer to give up the Houſe, with the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall, Ammunition, and Ordnance, ſo that they might march away with their Armes and Horſes. Which though it might by ſome that waigh not the ſeverall circumſtances be eſteemed too ſpecious adeparture for them, yet this prudent Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man conſidering the Houſe was ſtrong, that it had coſt ſome men already, and that he could not force it, but at dearer rates, choſe rather to yeeld to their demands, then hazard the lives of any more; which were more precious to him then the Armes of the Rebells. Vpon their ſurrender, he ſo punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally obſerv'd his Conditions, and convoy'd them with ſuch civility, that themſelves confeſt they had fallen into the hands of an honourable and gallant Enemy.</p>
            <p>His ſucceſſe here procured him freſh imployments, he is ſent to diſturbe their new garriſon at <hi>Abingd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> to effect which he marcht out in the night, and preſuming of the intelligence of thoſe who had imployed him concerning the Forces of the Enemy, He falls upon them gallantly in the morning, and charges up to their turnepikes and aſcends their workes, but finding the enemy powre upon him in ſuch unexpected num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, he begins to think of a retreat, and give immediat order for it: As being the only thing they could hope for, if that; conſidering as well the enemies ſtrength and readineſſe as the thinneneſſe of their own numbers, their diſtance from hom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113225:7"/> their amazement and repulſe: but ſuch was his valour dexteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and diſcretion, that notwithſtanding the enemy purſued him like a torrent, he made an honourable and ſafe Retreat.</p>
            <p>This added much to his eſteem in the judgement of every knowing and diſcreet man. So that what imployment of exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and neceſſity this Summer afforded here, was almoſt all impoſed upon him; <hi>Baſing Caſtle,</hi> the dwelling houſe of the Honourable and Loyall <hi>Marqueſſe of Wincheſter,</hi> had now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured a ſecond Siege for two and twenty weekes: and was now brought to that neceſſity for Proviſions, that unleſſe it were ſupplied by a ſpeedy reliefe, it muſt be forced to ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. This once certified to the <hi>Commiſſioners at Oxford</hi> added much trouble to the exigence of their preſent condition. For they ſaw no ſuddain aſſiſtance could be expected from His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, they conſidered the importance of the place; the quality and gallant behaviour of the defendants, together with their owne inabilities to aſſiſt them; which concurrence of diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties made them very anxious, till conſulting with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Gage,</hi> they find him beyond expectation proffer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe voluntarily to run the hazard of all obſtructions, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake the buſineſſe. Though here they conſidered that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bingdo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Ailysbury, Reading,</hi> and the <hi>Leaguer</hi> it ſelfe, did ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally afford greater numbers then they could ſend with him, though they waighed the length of the March, and difficulty of the paſſes; yet ſuch was their opinion in him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in his Courage, and experience, that they reſigned all to his diſcretion. The action was ſo eminent and ſo deſerving memory, ſo Souldier like and fortunately attempted, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, that I cannot pretend to honour his <hi>Noble Genius,</hi> ſhould I omit a punctuall relation of it.</p>
            <p>Vpon <hi>Monday</hi> the ninth of <hi>September,</hi> that at ten a clock at night, he Marcht out of <hi>Oxford</hi> towards <hi>Baſing.</hi> with 400 Foot, 250 Horſe. 12 barrells of Powder, 1200 waight of Match, paſſes by <hi>Wallingford,</hi> where he received an addition of 80 Horſe, with as many Foot, on <hi>Tueſday</hi> Morning they reſted and refreſhed, and then he diſpatched an expreſſe to the Governour of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> Sir <hi>William Ogle,</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſirine him,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113225:8"/> according to his former promiſe to Sir <hi>Edward Nicholas</hi> to draw out with his Forces, and to fall into <hi>Baſing</hi> Parke, in the reare of the Rebells Quarters, betwixt foure and five a clock the next Morning, being <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>September:</hi> whileſt he with the <hi>Oxford</hi> Troopes aſſaulted them on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, and the <hi>Lord Marqueſſe</hi> from the Houſe, plyed them with a fierce Sally. Having finiſht this diſpatch, he Marcht forward, with as much ſpeed as the Foot Souldiers could make, towards <hi>Aldermerſton,</hi> where he intended to repoſe againe. They paſt through the Country for <hi>Parliamenteers,</hi> with O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range tawney Scarfes and ribands, till a <hi>Wallingford Captaine</hi> (who was ſent before with his Troope, together with the Quarter-maſters of each Regiment to diſcover, and have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions in a readineſſe againſt the Souldiers arrived) found in the Towne, ſome of the enemies Scoutes, and forgetting his diſguiſe fell fowle upon them, took ſome Priſoners and ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd themſelves. This evening the Foot were extreamly wearied (having had ſcarce 3 houres reſt ſince they went out of <hi>Oxford</hi>) which the prudent Colonell perceiving<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> alighted himſelfe from his Horſe, by whoſe example and intreaty, the other Officers, and Troopers did the like, and walkt three miles, whileſt the tired Foot refreſht themſelves in their Saddles; By which meanes, he came to <hi>Aldermerſton</hi> about eight in the evening; ſeven miles from <hi>Baſing,</hi> and reſted till eleven, when againe he ſet forward and Marcht all night, though the Foot were faint and much dejected. So that being come within two miles of the place, they began to lye downe as not able to advance farther, whereupon he cauſed all his Horſe-men every man to take one of them up behind him, himſelfe giving the firſt example, which u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo took them, that they wholly forgot their former <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>gue, and with hopes of Pillage, and promiſe of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>Oxford,</hi> were ſo encouraged, that they deſired no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more then to attaque the Rebell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>In the interim, arrives a Lie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ant from <hi>Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cheſter,</hi> who a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>res them, the Governour by reaſon of the Enemies Horſe, which lay betwixt him and <hi>Baſing,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not draw <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t to aſſiſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113225:8"/> them. Whereupon the <hi>Colonell</hi> was compell'd to enter into new Counſells; wherefore ſeeing himſelfe deprived of that aſſiſtance, and preſuming the Enemy having notice of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, would draw to a head, he reſolves contrary to his firſt reſolutions, with united Forces to fall ſtrongly upon them in one place. In order to which he Commands the men to be put in readineſſe, riding up to every Squadron, gave the word, which was <hi>Saint George,</hi> chearing them with what poſſible encouragements he could, and Commanding every of them to tye a handkerchiefe on their right armes above their elblow, for a diſtinction to be knowne as well to one another, as to the <hi>Lord Marqueſſe</hi> his men, if they ſhould chance to make a Sally, and for want of ſuch a ſignall fall foule upon one another.</p>
            <p>After this preparation, they marched on, the gallant Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell alighting from his Horſe, arm'd only with his Sword, led up the Foot, and being come as he conceived, within hearing of the Houſe, he Command his Drummes and Trumpets to cheare the beſieged with the newes of his long wiſht arrivall. The Rebells having notice the day before of his comming, and of the place he was like to fall on, had drawne forth all their beſt men, all freſh and pamper'd in number farre excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his, with theſe they poſſeſt the Paſſes, with ſome croſſe hedges of advantage, lining them with Musketiers.</p>
            <p>Here ſtood the reſt of the Horſe and Foot in <hi>Batagli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ready for him, and anſwer'd his Drummes and Trumpets with their owne, which he perceived were very neare, though clouded under the wing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of an obſcure miſt. Our Forces had advanced not many paces further, before they diſcovered a Body of the Enemies Horſe, conſiſting of ſixe Troopes, ſtanding in very good order ready to receive our charge. Which though we haſtened to acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt them with, before we came at them, we were firſt ſaluted from the hedges by a ſmart Volley of Musket ſhot, though accompanied with more Terror then Execution: for notwithſtanding this, the right wing of our Horſe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by gallant Colonell <hi>Webb:</hi> Charg'd the Enemy ſo home, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they all turn'd head and ran away. The left wing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> after the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> followed the Chaſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> till the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113225:9"/> Rebells were got into a place of ſafety. In this purſuit, we took a Cornet of theirs, which ſince is knowne to be <hi>Morleyes.</hi> Vpon the Rout of the Horſe, <hi>Colonell Gage</hi> advanced with the Foot towards the hedges, where after two houres diſpute, he beat them from hedge to hedge, till at laſt he brought them to abandon all their holdes on that ſide, and give him free en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance to the Houſe. Where after he had delivered the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition he brought with him, and paid my Lord <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> the reſpects due to a Perſon of his quality, leaving 100 Souldiers of his owne with him, he marcht with the reſt of the Horſe and Foot to <hi>Baſingstoke;</hi> a good halfe mile diſtant thence, and with ſmall reſiſtance poſſeſt himſelfe of it; whence all that day he continued ſending to the Garriſon, as much Wheat, Malt, Salt, Oates, Bacon, Cheeſe, Butter, and other Proviſion, as he could get Carts or Horſes to tranſport it. There he found a little Magazine of 13 Barrells of Powder, with ſome Muskets, which alſo he ſent in: together with 80 head of Cattle, and 100 ſheep. Whil'ſt theſe things were doing at <hi>Baſingstoke,</hi> according to his directions, they in the Houſe Sallyed into <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> Town, beat thence the Enemy, killing 50, and taking two of their Captaines, and 33 Souldiers Priſoners in the Church.</p>
            <p>By this time the day was neare ſpent, and the Enemy ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving received ſome freſh ſupplies of Horſe, appeared much more numerous, and gay then in the morning, and made ſhew of a deſire to fight with ours againe. Advancing to that end over a large Champaine, almoſt within Musket ſhot of our Horſe, ſtanding in a field without <hi>Baſingſtoke,</hi> betwixt two large Hedges, which were lined with Foot. There they ſtood facing each other an houre or two, till the Colonell perceived his Squadrons of Horſe to grow thin, many of them ſlincking away by reaſon of the extreame fatigue and faſting, wherewith moſt of them both Horſe and Men were oppreſt. Whereupon he gave order they ſhould retire by degrees, and paſſe through the Towne towards <hi>Baſing</hi> houſe, whilſt he with the Foot made good the Avenues and Paſſages, on that ſide the Tow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. When he underſtood the Troopes had paſt the Towne, and were put againe into order on the other ſide towards the houſe.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113225:9"/> He likewiſe with moſt part of the Foot, retired likewiſe, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Captaine with 70 Musketeers to make good the Ave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue; who alſo when he ſaw the Colonell retired up to the Horſe, drew off alſo, leaving only a Sergeant with 20, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute the Paſſage, till the reſt were retired into the Houſe. Whither they alſo had order immediately to draw off, which they did, the Enemy not once attempting to enter the Towne: but retreating ſoon after, they perceived our Horſe to give back. The reaſon why this provident Commander refuſed to lodge in the Towne, was the conſideration of the many Ave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues to be defended, againſt the Enemy now recruited with new additions of ſtrength; which could not without difficulty have been done, in regard our Horſe and Men were ſo farre ſpent, and our Souldiers ſo apt to hide and diſperſe in ſeverall houſes, there to fall to drinking and diſorders.</p>
            <p>The next day early he ſent out a Lievtenant Colonell to the Towne with all the Horſe and Foot, as well to refreſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as to be ſending Proviſions all that day into the Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. In the meane while this accompliſht Souldier ſpent that <hi>Thurſday</hi> in contriveing his retreat to <hi>Oxford,</hi> and ſending out ſeverall Spies to obſerve the motions of another Enemy, who was drawing to a head from <hi>Abington, Newbury,</hi> and <hi>Reading,</hi> to hinder his retreat homewards. And he found by the unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous relation of his ſeverall Spies, that they of <hi>Abington</hi> were lodged at <hi>Aldermarſton,</hi> they of <hi>Newbury</hi> at <hi>Thatcham,</hi> and they of <hi>Reading</hi> at <hi>Padſworth,</hi> Townes lying upon ſeverall paſſes of the River <hi>Kennet,</hi> over which He was neceſſitated to goe; in his retreat <hi>Norton</hi> with his Horſe and Foot which lay in <hi>Baſing</hi> Parke, was to follow him in the Reare, whenſoever he began to move, which they conceived he could not doe, but they ſhould have notice of it. The <hi>Colonell</hi> reſolved there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in his owne breaſt, without acquainting any man whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with it, to make his retreat that very night, having in that little time he had been there ſlaine ſixeſcore, taken 100 Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, with 150 Armes, and out of the adjacent Townes, put in a Monthes Proviſion into the Houſe. As alſo drawne in two peeces of the Enemies Artillery; The one, a goodly <hi>Demi-Cannon,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:113225:10"/> which had been formerly engaged, and neither Party had adventured to fetch them off.</p>
            <p>But now the better to amuſe the Enemy, and give them cauſe to thinke that He thought of nothing leſſe then of ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine a retreat, he ſent out Warrants to <hi>Sherborne</hi> and <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> (preſuming they would come to the Enemies know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) to bring in ſuddainly a certaine quantity of Corne to the Garriſon upon pain, if they refuſed, of ſending 1000 Horſe and Dragoones before the next day noone to ſet their Townes on fire. Having thus diſpoſed of all things within himſelfe, and judging that he was not able with longer ſtay to doe my <hi>Lord Marqueſſe</hi> any further ſervice: though by delaying his returne, he might have endangered the loſſe of thoſe Forces committed to his Charge. A little before night, he ſent Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to <hi>Baſingstoke,</hi> for his men to retire, as they had done the night before, and to march to the Houſe, but not to enter, till they had further Order from him: whither when they were arrived, he told my <hi>Lord Marqueſſe</hi> of his reſolution to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part that night, and the neceſſity of it; begging of him two or three good Guides, and ſo takes leave of his Lordſhip, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching away quietly without ſound of Drum or Trumpet about eleven of the clock that Thurſday night. He gives Orders to all his Scouts both in the Van and Reare, that if they met with any of the Enemy, they ſhould likewiſe give themſelves out to be <hi>Parliamenteers,</hi> marching from the Campe before <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi> to the River <hi>Kennet,</hi> to lye in wait for the <hi>Oxford</hi> Forces that were to retire that way; Thus as you ſee his judgement and prudence was excelling, ſo his Succeſſe was equall. For finding the <hi>Rebels</hi> had pull'd downe <hi>Burfield-Bridge,</hi> he found a way to foard the River, every Trooper taking up a Musketier behind him.</p>
            <p>So having happily paſt the <hi>Kennet,</hi> and having certaine no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice they had pulled up both <hi>Henly</hi> and <hi>Reading Bridges;</hi> about eight a clock on Friday morning, he did againe foard the <hi>Thames</hi> at <hi>Pangborne,</hi> and ſo marcht to <hi>Wallingford,</hi> where he reſted and refreſht that night, arriving ſafe the next day at <hi>Oxford,</hi> with the loſſe onely of eleven men. Where he was
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113225:10"/> received with extraordinary applauſe, and acclamations<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though he ſhow'd as much diſcretion and modeſty upon that occaſion, as he had done Valour and Prudence in the Action that procur'd it. For when upon notice of his approach, moſt of the people ran out into the fields to meet him, and all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of quality almoſt with their Coaches went to honour his returne, he ſteales away by them, and after he is enter'd the Towne, rides up a private way to his lodging, as if he had been nothing concerned in theſe expreſſions of joy; and as if this triumph had had no relation to him. Which the people refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting upon, when as the Souldiers entred the Towne, they ſaw him abſent whom they ſtood gazing to behold; I meane the wiſe Conductor of this great &amp; fortunate enterprize, who privately had withdrawne himſelfe. Which turned their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe to wonder, and hence they doubly magnified ſo admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable a Perſon.</p>
            <p>But whether this great Action were undertaken with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter magnanimity, performed with more Courage, Prudence, &amp; Skill, or finiſhed with more modeſty, I dare not preſume to reſolve. Yet I dare affirme, that if you conſider all circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and difficulties, this Expert Gallant Commander paſt through in the performing of it: as for example his fighting with a ſtrength ſo farre ſuperiour to his, at ſo great a diſtance, from friends and home, upon their owne ground, and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all treacherous endeavours to the contrary, to mannage and performe it with ſuch ſecrecy and Succeſſe: nay, after all though way laid in ſundry places, with ſuch vaſt numbers, who had broke the Bridges, and poſſeſt the Paſſes, to make ſuch a Gallant and ſafe Retreat. This weig'd, I ſay you needs muſt grant the whole Action to have been for wiſe Conduct, gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant and ſkilfull manage, the moſt Souldier-like piece theſe Warres have ever yet afforded.</p>
            <p>Few weeks are paſt after this, before <hi>Banbury</hi> alſo is brought into the like exigent condition, and muſt needs be releived by ſuch a time or elſe ſurrendred. Wherefore to him again they have recourſe, as to the only perſon that could effect it. He to convince the world, that his zeale and love to his Majeſty was
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113225:11"/> the cheife motive of his undertaking, and to evince them who attributed his cheerfull undergoing the laſt action, only to his reſpect and affection to that moſt noble and loyall Lord, the <hi>Marqueſſe of Wincheſter.</hi> Embraces this imployment alſo though he eſteemed it a peice of greater difficulty then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, as then he told the Lords Commiſſioners, by reaſon now it was with the ſame number to encounter an Enemy doubly equall to the other; notwithſtanding which, their confidence and opinion of him is ſuch that he muſt needs attempt it, and and to engage h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m further, they aſſure him the King will ſend the Earle of <hi>Northampton</hi> with 400 Horſe to his aſſiſtance, and that punctually at ſuch a time and place they ſhould come and meet him. He wiſely conſider'd that the force of <hi>Oxford</hi> joyn'd with them, were not conſiderable to fall upon an Enemy triple their number, if either ski<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l or reſolution did attend them. Wherefore he concludes by ſome ſtratageme or other to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate them, and lay a foundation whereupon he might proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly raiſe the deſired ſucceſſe; to this end he counterfaits the hand of <hi>Browne</hi> Commander of the <hi>Rebels</hi> at <hi>Abingdon,</hi> and directs a letter to <hi>Fines</hi> at <hi>Banbury,</hi> aſſuring him the King was come with a formidable Army to <hi>Newbury,</hi> and that he was ſending the Earle of <hi>Northampton</hi> with 3000 Horſe and Dragoones which were to paſſe by <hi>Abingdon,</hi> and to joyne with <hi>Gage,</hi> and the <hi>Oxford</hi> Forces in raiſing that Seidge. Wherefore he Counſells him to depart, and draw off in time, for by reaſon of the neerneſſe of the Kings Army, he could not afford him any aſſiſtance. This letter was by his contrivall handſomly delivered, and ſo amuzed <hi>Fines,</hi> that he called a Councell of War upon it, which ſate ſome houres. The hand perſwaded them that <hi>Browne</hi> had ſent it, only one of them creates a doubt in the ſmoothneſſe of the ſtile, and inſiſts upon that, which cauſes them before they reſolve any thing, to ſend a Poſt to <hi>Abingdon</hi> to know if any ſuch letter were ſent thence, where all was diſavow'd, <hi>Browne</hi> proteſting nothing came from him. This anſwer made them again ſecure, but ſo that they kept ſtrict watch upon all quarters to diſcover any moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ours. Not many houres after the Earle of <hi>Northampton</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:113225:11"/> cames with about the firſt mentioned number, and noble Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell <hi>Gage</hi> according to their pact goes out with ſome Foot, two Drakes and what Horſe the Towne afforded to meet him; upon this the Enemies Scouts at their approach run in, and aſſures them that the <hi>Earle</hi> and <hi>Colonell</hi> were now comming indeed; immediatly they apprehend themſelves betraid, and conclude, that the number and other circumſtances in the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſititious Letter, were all true. Whereupon they draw off their Cannon, and poſſeſt with a panick feare, ſend them away in the night: ſtaying themſelves till morning, for the honour to be ſo ſoundly beaten, that they could not lay claime to the credit of a Cowardly retreat. But flying give way to them, whom they might have devoured<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> had they ſtoutly ſtood and cloſed boldly with them, but the Succeſſe next after Almighty God is due to the diſcreet contrivall, and manage of this hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome device of his.</p>
            <p>Shortly after his returne from <hi>Banbury,</hi> His Majeſty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paires to <hi>Oxford,</hi> and as an earneſt of His Princely gratitude for theſe gallant Actions makes him a <hi>Knight,</hi> and treats him with very endearing reſpects, aſſuring him, that He would never forget his merit and ſingular Service: but ſtudy to advance him to ſuch honourable imployments as He might thence per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive how much He did value and eſteeme him. Which He ſhortly after perform'd, by making him Governour of <hi>Oxford;</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur Aſton,</hi> by reaſon of his unfortunate miſchance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing become unable for ſuch an active and toilſome Charge. It is incredible what a generall Contentment all men took in his Promotion, and how few repined at his advancement. And 'tis no leſſe difficult in thoſe that did not ſee it, to conceive how admirably well he manag'd that place, for thoſe few dayes he liv'd to poſſeſſe it. What noble and wiſe Deſignes he laid, with what admirable dexterity he endear'd himſelfe to all Courtiers, Scholars, Towneſmen, Souldiers, all affording him honour and affection. 'Tis really a wonder, how inſenſibly he fortified himſelfe in every ones opinion. He wins the Stateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man by his Prudence, the Courtier with Civility, the Scholar by his Reſpect to Arts, and Eminence therein, the Towneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113225:12"/> by C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rteſie, as alſo by falling halfe his owne Pay, and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them of many unneceſſary Taxes. Laſtly his Care, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and Gallantry endear'd him wholly to the Souldiers.</p>
            <p>He was no ſooner confirmed in his place, but he began to let the World perceive, that he meant to governe the Towne indeed, he takes an exact ſurvey of the Fortifications, Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zine, together with the number and diſcipline of the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and determines to ſee them all ſupplied, repreſenting them ſeriouſly to His Majeſties Councell, he does not onely expoſe the neceſſities and defects, but alſo propoſes the meanes how to ſupply and correct them. He demands Horſe to Command the Country, ſecure the Markets, and to fetch Proviſions to his Garriſon, and propounds the manner how to raiſe them, and doe all this. He takes order for ſtore againſt a Siedge, thence deſcends to the accommodation of the Souldier, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire and preſervation of their Armes. Diverſly contrives the Towneſmens eaſe, and yet performes it with content to the Souldier, and meanes of their better ſubſiſtance. Having done this at home, he begins to caſt his eyes abroad, and thinkes how to ſecure the Country, as much as was within the reach of poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility, whil'ſt the Enemy holds <hi>Abington:</hi> to the end, that they might be better able to Contribute and afford Proviſions to <hi>Oxford.</hi> Wherefore he reſolves to break all the Bridges upon the <hi>Tame,</hi> and the other Rivers neare, and to make redoubts upon the Fords and Paſſes, ſo to preſerve all the Eaſt and North ſide of the City entire from annoyance, and in other places to make Garriſons in places convenient; Theſe, and an hundred other excellent Deſignes he had, which if God had granted him Life, he would have accompliſht. All which, as all his other buſineſſe, he had chalk'd out for execution, in a gallant diſcreet method, which did the buſineſſe home, and yet left him in all without anger or aſperſion from any. Which in a moment, got him ſuch an exceſſe of love and authority toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that all concluded, never Towne could be more happy then this was like ere long to be. But ſcarce had we poſſeſt this admirable Man three weeks, and ſolac'd our ſelves in ſuch a treaſure. When the Heavens envious of our felicity, or
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113225:12"/> angry at our deſertleſſe happineſſe, in love with thoſe beauties and excellencies of his, were pleas'd to deprive us of him; making uſe of this occaſion. He ſeeing the exigence of ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Eaſt ſide of this City, to urge the demoliſhing of <hi>Columb</hi> Bridge neare <hi>Abington,</hi> over which the Enemy made daily incurſions into the Country to Plunder, gather Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions, and ſpoyle our Markets: Reſolv'd upon the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize and gives inſtruction to his Lievtenant Governour for the execution of it, he determining himſelfe to attend his Government at home. But it was the will of God to bereave us of him, his Autumne was come, and he muſt dye in the Bed of Honour. In order to which decree, thoſe tranſcendent gallant Spirits, who went in that Action out of their extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary eſteeme of him by power and entreaties, wooe him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his owne principles to leave his domeſtique charge, and expoſe himſelfe in that fatall attempt.</p>
            <p>Wherefore he drawes out of <hi>Oxford,</hi> with 600 Horſe and Foot, accompanied with the two Princely <hi>Brothers,</hi> P. <hi>Rupert,</hi> and P. <hi>Maurice,</hi> together with ſundry other gallant Spirits, who upon Saturday the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> came thither about ſeven in the morning, where this worthy Commander lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the men himſelfe, poſſeſt the Bridge. Making it good a long time againſt the hot aſſaults of the enraged Enemy, who endeavoured to preſerve the freedome of ſo important a Paſſe; which conduced ſo much to their ſubſiſtance, and our annoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. The diſpute was ſo ſharp on both ſides, that the place was won and loſt no leſſe then twice on each ſide; the noble <hi>Colonell</hi> ſeeing the difficulty, had drawne himſelfe to a place convenient to ſurvey and conſider in ſuch manner the ſitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and acceſſes of advantage, that he might the better thereby attaine his end. Where whil'ſt he was deſigning how to purſue with ſucceſſe, what he had with ſuch difficulty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, a wandring Bullet hits him on the ſide, and tranſpierces his Body: with which mortall wound be immediatly falls to the ground, and together with him the whole enterprize, which was preſently deſerted.</p>
            <p>Shortly after this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſhment of this mortall Summons
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113225:13"/> was paſt over, he comes to himſelfe, and being taken up to be conveyed away, recollects his powers, to prepare himſelfe for his approaching end. Which with great piety and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence he performed, with no little edification to ſuch as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd him. At this inſtant he gave an ample teſtimony of the ſincerity and reſolution wherewith he came to ſerve His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and his Country in this juſt Quarrell. For being deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded what he would have done concerning his temporall Eſtate, he replied; <hi>I thank God, that, to my comfort is already ſetled, onely Commend me to my deare Wife, and put her in mind, that if it can be, ſhee ſee my Sonnes brought up according as ſhee and I had agreed, ſo many yeares at Schoole, where they are, and after ſend them to</hi> LA FLESH <hi>in</hi> FRANCE, <hi>to heare ſome part of their Philoſophy, and to learne thoſe other neceſſary and becomming qualities of Gentlemen. Tell my Children, that their dying Father ſends them his Bleſſing.</hi> Except theſe few wordes in all the time of at leaſt two houres, which he lived in perfect ſence and memory after that unfortunate wound: he was not heard to open his mouth to any other end, then to breath forth Heroike acts of Devotion, attending wholly to reconcile himſelfe to his Lord and Saviour, into whoſe divine hands with unſpeakable reſignation and repoſe he yeelded his happy Soule.</p>
            <p>The newes of this ſad diſaſter comming before, prepared <hi>Oxford</hi> to entertaine his Body with ſuch a face of ſorrow, as I am deceiv'd, if ever formerly had been ſeen ſuch a generall dejection, and lamentations ſo univerſall in that City, amongſt all degrees of Perſons. And it was well obſerv'd, that the moſt generous and noble Spirits did moſt paſſionately expreſſe their affection, and reſent the loſſe of this renowned Gentleman. But this appeared moſt abundantly in the Confluxe at his Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall on the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> where the Court, the Camp, the Vniverſity, the City, did even contend who ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the greateſt affection, and yeeld him the greateſt honour. The <hi>Court</hi> honour'd him with <hi>Prince Rupert,</hi> the <hi>Duke of Richmond,</hi> the <hi>Lord Treaſurer,</hi> the <hi>Lords Chamberlaines Secretaries, Comptroller,</hi> the <hi>Lords of the Privy Councell;</hi> and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113225:13"/> moſt of the Nobility and Gentry beſides. The <hi>Camp</hi> ſends Deputies of her affection, moſt of the great <hi>Commanders</hi> in the Kingdome. The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> and <hi>City,</hi> afford both their repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative Bodies in the <hi>Vice-Chancellor</hi> and <hi>Mayor,</hi> with their ſeverall Traines of followers. <hi>Somerſet</hi> and <hi>Cheſter Heralds</hi> were ſent by His Majeſty to attend, and order the ſolemnity, which was indeed worthily perform'd. The Souldiers did guard the paſſage from the thronging multitude, whil'ſt foure Trumpets in mourning went before, beating the aire with the dolefull Ecchoes, you may imagine this ſad occaſion did afford, which they continued, till they had brought to <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> (to uſe the <hi>Heralds</hi> words) <hi>The moſt Honourable Sir Henry Gage Governour of Oxford,</hi> who in the North <hi>Angle</hi> in the Body of the Church, was at length depoſited, his Grave being honour'd with the Teares and Sighes of our whole Nation Epitomiz'd in this City. Amongſt which my affection doth perforce oblige me to preſerve the memory of my affliction for this irreparable diſaſter, in the following <hi>Elegy.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <head>An ELEGY.</head>
               <l>AS flowers, whoſe lovely tinctures moſt invite</l>
               <l>Our eyes, and feed them with the chaſt delight</l>
               <l>Of naked beauties, which our ſenſes chaine</l>
               <l>With choicest odors nature doth containe:</l>
               <l>Charming our ſight more ſtrongly to behold,</l>
               <l>The Bodies that theſe rarities enfold;</l>
               <l>Intice us nearer, which doth alſo woo</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s both to handle, and to cull them too:</l>
               <l>Neglecting others which were theſe away,</l>
               <l>Were worth our notice, and a like ſurvay.</l>
               <l>So men whoſe faire perfections beſt proclaime;</l>
               <l>The fountaine whence thoſe excellencies came</l>
               <l>With life and vigour; inſomuch thereby</l>
               <l>That Atheiſts urg'd confeſſe a Deity:</l>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:113225:14"/>
               <l>Such whoſe Heroike mindes and nobler ſoules</l>
               <l>The worlds great axe-tree out of both the poles</l>
               <l>Would caſt, in conteſtation to <hi>inthrone</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Juſtice and vertue, though they loſt their <hi>owne.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Men in whoſe boſomes ſhines immortall light,</l>
               <l>Enricht with all that is not infinite.</l>
               <l>No ſooner theſe doth luſtfull Heaven ſpye,</l>
               <l>But fixes on them an inamour'd eye:</l>
               <l>And eager loveſicke. This diſeaſe to cure,</l>
               <l>Purloynes them from us, ere they be mature.</l>
               <l>Thus thus alas Great <hi>GAGE,</hi> from earth was cull'd,</l>
               <l>Long time before the hand of nature pull'd.</l>
               <l>Bleſt <hi>Genius,</hi> if thou be not quite diſſolv'd,</l>
               <l>Into that endleſſe eſſence which involv'd</l>
               <l>All eſſences, or if thou ſtill deſcry</l>
               <l>Within the mirrour of the Deity,</l>
               <l>Our wordes and actions: if thou take delight</l>
               <l>To live preſerved from Cymmer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an night</l>
               <l>In humane boſomes. Heark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n to the vow,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto thy happy Ghost I offer now,</l>
               <l>By all the love I bore thy precious breath,</l>
               <l>By all the teares wherein I mourn'd thy death,</l>
               <l>By all the honours that thy vertues Crown'd,</l>
               <l>By all the joyes wherein thou doſt abound,</l>
               <l>By all that bliſſe thou doeſt poſſeſſe and ſee,</l>
               <l>By all thoſe glories that invelope thee,</l>
               <l>I here proteſt, thy name ſhall never dye,</l>
               <l>Whilſt any thing is mortall, that is I.</l>
               <l>Nay my immortall part, ſhall ever pay</l>
               <l>Homage to thee in that Eternall day</l>
               <l>Of endleſſe time, in which thou ſhalt deſcry</l>
               <l>My love as freſh as immortality.</l>
            </lg>
            <bibl>Ed: Walſingham.</bibl>
            <p>I have hitherto inſiſted upon what this noble Gentleman did his Life and Actions; give me leave now in briefe to tell you what he was, and give you a ſcantling both of his inward
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113225:14"/> and outward man. Sir <hi>Henry Gage,</hi> was of a faire and goodly Stature, in Body as in mind, above the ordinary pitch of other men; To this height he had in all parts a beautifull propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. He was of a faire Complexion, very Comely, his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment was Courteous, Gentile, and his Preſence full of Reverence: His Speech diſcreet and civill, his Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion pleaſant, very modeſt, and accommodated happily to places, times, and Perſons. In fine his gratious outſide, did every where proclaime what a rich and noble Soule was lodg'd within.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that were pleas'd to take notice of what he ſaid and did, continually diſcovered new proportions of Vertue in him, and the ſtricter their obſervation was, ſo much the more did they admire his Vertues and Abilities, of ſome whereof at leaſt, I have engag'd my ſelfe to give a ſhort account. What was moſt ſingular in him was his perpetuall induſtry, and that even when he was not in actuall Service in the field, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing his Souldiers in the uſe of their Armes, cutting out Townes and Forts in Turfe, and teaching his men even by way of recreation how to become expert; how to Approach, to Scale, Retreat, how to gaine a Towne by Aſſault, or by a famiſhing Siedge, how to make their Trenches, and ſecure themſelves, with a Thouſand ſuch Souldier-like imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>He had an excellent Pen, and that ſtrangely enricht by the variety of the beſt Languages whereof he was Maſter; <hi>Latine, Engliſh, French, Italian, Spaniſh,</hi> were familiar unto him; he was not ignorant in <hi>Greek,</hi> and though he was in <hi>Dutch</hi> not elegant, yet he had enough to treat with the Peaſants there, and ſuch as underſtood no other language, all which is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame argument of a ſtrong memory. His ability in this kind made him imcomparable gratefull to all, for being in a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try where all Languages were ſpoken, he was able to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine every one for the moſt part in his owne Tongue. Which made him eminent in a high degree, as appeared at the Siedge of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Omers,</hi> at which time by reaſon of a <hi>Pueſto</hi> he had Charge of there, he having frequent occaſions to ſend ſundry Orders
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113225:15"/> and diſpatches in ſeverall Languages, <hi>Prince Thomas of Savoy;</hi> took ſpeciall notice thereof, and perceiving they came alwaies in the ſame hand, enquired who was his Secretary. Anſwer being made, that he uſed none, he admired it ſo farre, that to be further aſſured, he ſent a <hi>Walloon Cavalier,</hi> called <hi>Monſeiur Lanoy,</hi> with ſome pretended buſineſſe to ſtay with him; though the true end was to take notice whether or no he was his owne Secretary, being that his Stile and Language was ſtill ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent good. The truth is, there are not many that are able in ſo ſeverall Languages, without affectation to write ſuch natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally elegant and gentile Letters, with ſo much facility and diſpatch.</p>
            <p>How patient he was of labour, and how carefull of his Charge, I need goe no further for an inſtance then his laſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, the Government of <hi>Oxford;</hi> which appear'd remarkable to all the Inhabitants; for after he had ſo great a truſt committed by His Majeſty unto him, there was no night in which he ſlept foure houres in his Bed, for being buſied all day he took the dead of the night to write and contrive his Affaires. Which thoſe prudent and Souldier-like inſtructions he left behind him worthily demonſtrate. Yet all this ſerious attention to warlike affaires did not ſo much poſſeſſe him, but they left him enough of himſelfe to attend to Converſation, which was ſo affable and Courtly, that thoſe who were ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to him, dream'd often of nothing leſſe then that he was a Commander of ſo much Courage, Experience, and Repute.</p>
            <p>As none in the Summer was more active in the field in the times of his imployment then he; ſo none in another kind more induſtrious in his Winter Garriſons. For then he was at Court perpetually ſoliciting in behalfe of his Souldiers, for their Pay, accommodations in Garriſons, recruits, and the like. You might ſee him alſo frequent in the Courts of Iuſtice, ſoliciting his right in Law in behalfe of his Wife and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; wherein he was ſo knowing, that all his Lawyers for the moſt part ingenuouſly ſtill confeſt, that he needed no better Councell then himſelfe had given unto them, by way of information in his Caſe. And however many able men
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113225:15"/> hold it action enough to follow any Suit in Law, yet he was more induſtrious then to waſt his whole day in this, or his Regiments affaires, and would ſteale beſides three, foure, or five cloſe houres to his Book and Pen, beſtowing himſelfe now in reading Hiſtory or Philoſophy, then in tranſlating ſome profitable Bookes, and ſometimes in writing ſomething of his owne; which as they highly deſerve, may chance ere long to be expos'd in publique, and communicated to the World. But his chiefe Study was to make himſelfe Maſter of the Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Warre, wherein though his practice was already emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, yet I may well affirme that none deſirous of Philoſophy ever ſtudied <hi>Aristotle</hi> more intenſely then he did Fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, Siedges, Mannaging of Battailes, and in generall the whole Stratagetick part of Warre.</p>
            <p>Nor was he yet ſo narrow, as with all this action to be Commenſurated, he found time enough, beſides twice or thrice a day to Comply with the obligations of a devout Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and moſt houres of the day with a great dexterity of his ready Pen to diſpatch Military orders, and correſpond con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly with divers Friends as well remote as neare unto him. Inſomuch that ſome wiſe men ſtick'd not to affirme him a man made for as much Action, as was neceſſary to mannage the affaires of a great Empire. Which may be confirm'd by the greatneſſe of his mind, and ſtrange liberality, which even ſince his comming hither he hath ſometimes practiced. Once he was knowne when he had but three and forty ſhillings in all, and knew not how at preſent to compaſſe more, he ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to give forty of it to a decayed Gentleman, that beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of him, whereupon being adviſed to husband better his money, till his imployments would afford him more plenty, he ſmiling anſwered, <hi>When I begin to love money, I ſhall deſiſt to be any more a Souldier, for he that loves money loves his life, and by conſequence fearing danger, is unfit to be imploy'd in any gallant Action.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this was not the onely generous way he ſpent his meanes, for he laid out very much in Correſpondence, having
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113225:16"/> excellent good weekly from moſt parts of Chriſtendome, which although it was chargeable to him, yet he was wont to ſay; <hi>What others ſpent in Cards, Dice, and other vaine exerciſes, be might well allow himſelfe in this, which was ſo uſefull to him, and of ſo great contentment.</hi> The Honour of his Nation he had ſtill an eye upon, when he was abroad as well as his owne, and although his Revenue was not great, yet no <hi>Italian, Spaniard,</hi> or other <hi>Cavalier</hi> appeared more neat and gallant both in Field and Garriſon then he, who kept alwayes a conſtant Table, fit at any time to receive the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Commander. Which was alwayes grac'd with extreame Courteſie and freedome. Theſe diſcreet gallantries, gave a luſtre to his greater merits and eſteeme, and that not onely here at home, as the World ſaw with His Majeſty, the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, and all ſorts of People, but alſo in the Court of <hi>Brux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ells,</hi> and the whole Country. Where by reaſon of his Affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, Prudence, Valour, and other great endowments, he was reputed the flower of all our <hi>Engliſh</hi> that had appeared in thoſe parts. Though his worth and Perſon were admir'd and gratefull to all, yet to none more then thoſe three Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Generalls, <hi>Prince Thomas of Savoy,</hi> the <hi>Duke of Ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> and <hi>Count Fountaine,</hi> all which held with him an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary familiarity and dearneſſe, won by that chearfull calmneſſe and compoſure in him, which invited all men to admire his conſtant ſmoothneſſe ſo great, that the higheſt incitements would hardly adde a wrinkle to the ſeverity of his mind, to make his paſſion legible to ſuch as ſtudied him with moſt attention.</p>
            <p>Thus I have given you a briefe ſurvay of the Famous <hi>Gage,</hi> though I confeſſe, I have afforded you but a glimpſe of his inward man, and have willingly conceal'd the greateſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and excellencies of his richeſt Soule. I have done nothing in ſaying, all men knew him an expert <hi>Souldier,</hi> a great <hi>Commander,</hi> and that his Friends knew him a perfect <hi>Linguiſt,</hi> an excellent <hi>Humaniſt,</hi> a ſound <hi>Philoſopher;</hi> and competently ſeen in <hi>diviner Studies:</hi> in ſumme a compleat
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113225:16"/> 
               <hi>Scholar,</hi> inſomuch that it may well be doubted, whether he was abler at his <hi>Pike</hi> or <hi>Pen.</hi> I have added little by affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming him an exact <hi>Courtier,</hi> nay a prudent <hi>Stateſman;</hi> as ſome able judgements have not ſticked freely to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: unleſſe I did treat of his more inward Vertues, and diſcloſe his ſingular Piety. But ſeeing my ſelfe unfit, unable for to ſpeak him further, I here conclude; and offer this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Votive of my affection to his happy memory, glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that by this, Poſterity ſhall know me ſo, as at leaſt to ranke me amongſt the admirers of this excellent Man.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
